<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://gitb33rman.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://gitb33rman.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-06T12:31:13+00:00</updated><id>https://gitb33rman.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Feiko Bierman</title><subtitle>The personal website of Feiko Bierman. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Making sense of modern marketing tracking - a deep dive for e-commerce and lead generation</title><link href="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2025/tracking-setups/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making sense of modern marketing tracking - a deep dive for e-commerce and lead generation"/><published>2025-02-06T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-06T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2025/tracking-setups</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2025/tracking-setups/"><![CDATA[<p>In today’s digital landscape, proper tracking implementation is crucial for making informed business decisions. While my previous blogs focused on the advanced applications of marketing data through AI and cloud services, today I want to break down the fundamental building blocks that make these innovations possible. Let’s explore the essential elements for both e-commerce and lead generation implementations.</p> <p><strong>The foundation: consent and data collection</strong> Both implementation types share crucial foundational elements. A properly functioning cookie banner with consent mode integration isn’t just about legal compliance - it’s about respecting user privacy while ensuring accurate data collection. This setup allows us to adjust tracking behavior based on user consent, maintaining data quality without compromising privacy standards.</p> <h3 id="e-commerce-tracking-essentials">E-commerce tracking essentials</h3> <p><strong>The power of the dataLayer</strong> At the heart of e-commerce tracking lies a complete dataLayer implementation. This technical foundation captures enhanced e-commerce events and conversion parameters, providing detailed insights into the customer journey. From product impressions to purchase completion, each interaction is meticulously tracked, creating a comprehensive view of user behavior.</p> <p>Why is this so crucial? The enhanced e-commerce functionality allows you to:</p> <ul> <li>Analyze the complete shopping funnel</li> <li>Identify drop-off points in your checkout process</li> <li>Understand which products perform best in different contexts</li> <li>Measure the effectiveness of your product recommendations</li> </ul> <p><strong>Data preservation and analysis</strong> Two critical components ensure your data remains accessible and reliable:</p> <ol> <li>GA4 export to BigQuery ensures you maintain ownership of your raw data, enabling advanced analysis beyond GA4’s standard reporting</li> <li>Tag and dataLayer monitoring prevents data loss by alerting you to potential tracking issues before they impact your decision-making</li> </ol> <h3 id="lead-generation-tracking-foundations">Lead generation tracking foundations</h3> <p>Lead generation businesses face unique challenges in tracking and attributing success. The essential elements here focus on connecting online behavior with offline outcomes.</p> <p><strong>Enhanced conversions for lead quality</strong> Enhanced conversions for quote requests provide a more accurate picture of your conversion landscape. By implementing this feature, you can:</p> <ul> <li>Better understand which channels drive quality leads</li> <li>Improve your conversion attribution</li> <li>Make more informed decisions about marketing spend</li> </ul> <p><strong>The offline connection</strong> One strongly recommended element for lead generation businesses is offline conversion tracking. This feature allows you to:</p> <ul> <li>Feed actual deal values back into advertising platforms</li> <li>Optimize campaigns based on real business outcomes</li> <li>Improve algorithmic bidding performance</li> </ul> <h3 id="the-next-level-server-side-tagging">The next level: server-side tagging</h3> <p>For both implementation types, server-side tagging via a cloud provider represents a significant upgrade to your tracking infrastructure. This approach offers:</p> <ul> <li>Improved data quality and reliability</li> <li>Better performance for your website</li> <li>Enhanced privacy controls</li> <li>More flexibility in data collection and distribution</li> </ul> <h3 id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h3> <p>While these implementations form the foundation of modern marketing tracking, they’re just the beginning. As discussed in my previous blogs about AI integration and cloud capabilities, having this solid tracking foundation enables you to take advantage of advanced features like VertexAI and marketing mix modeling. More on that in future blogs.</p> <p>The key is to start with a robust implementation that matches your business model. Whether you’re in e-commerce or lead generation, these essential elements provide the data quality and completeness needed to drive business growth through data-driven decision making. Remember, the goal isn’t just to collect data - it’s to create a foundation that enables you to extract actionable insights and drive business value. By implementing these essential elements correctly, you’re setting yourself up for success in an increasingly data-driven digital landscape.</p> <p>What’s your experience with these tracking implementations? I’d love to hear about the challenges and successes you’ve encountered in your journey toward data-driven decision making.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Tracking_measurement"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A guide that breaks down the essential tracking elements for e-commerce and lead generation businesses, explaining why each component is crucial for building a foundation that enables data analysis and insights.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Future of E-commerce - Leveraging AI with Your GA4 Data</title><link href="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/future-e-commerce/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of E-commerce - Leveraging AI with Your GA4 Data"/><published>2024-07-30T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-30T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/future-e-commerce</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/future-e-commerce/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-next-step-in-data-analysis-from-tracking-to-ai-driven-insights">The Next Step in Data Analysis: From Tracking to AI-Driven Insights</h3> <p>In the world of digital marketing, we constantly hear about the importance of tracking. GA4 tracking, server-side tagging, consent mode - these have all become essential components of our digital infrastructure. But let’s be honest, in 2024, this should be basic knowledge for most digital players.</p> <p>The question that’s increasingly coming up with our clients is: “Okay, the tracking is set up. What now?” And that’s exactly where we need to focus our attention. How can we really make Google Analytics 4 data work for us?</p> <h3 id="from-data-to-action-with-google-cloud-platform">From Data to Action with Google Cloud Platform</h3> <p>Thanks to the free export options, the Google Cloud Platform offers a wealth of opportunities. But make no mistake - we’re not talking about standard dashboards or data warehouses here. The real potential lies in the latest innovation: AI.</p> <p>VertexAI, the AI hub within the Google Cloud Platform, opens doors to exciting possibilities. Take VertexAI Search for Retail, for example. This tool allows us to implement advanced product recommendation models and smart search functions, all based on your GA4 event data.</p> <h3 id="the-power-of-ai-driven-recommendations">The Power of AI-Driven Recommendations</h3> <p>Why is this so interesting? Firstly, it offers a more powerful model for product recommendations than many alternatives, potentially leading to more conversions. Additionally, it’s cost-efficient - often 4 to 5 times cheaper on a monthly basis than traditional SaaS solutions. The fact that major players like eBay.com use this functionality underscores its potential.</p> <p>Of course, it’s crucial to test whether this approach works for your specific situation. But it perfectly illustrates how we can look beyond just tracking.</p> <h3 id="the-future-of-data--analytics">The Future of Data &amp; Analytics</h3> <p>Tracking remains important, absolutely. But let’s broaden our view and look at the opportunities our field offers. The integration of AI with our GA4 data opens up a world of possibilities.</p> <p>How do you see the future? Are you already working on combining AI and your GA4 data? Let’s challenge each other and explore together what’s possible. Because it’s precisely in the synergy between data, technology, and human insight that the greatest opportunities for growth and innovation lie.</p> <p>The world of digital marketing is evolving at a rapid pace. By proactively embracing new technologies and experimenting, we can not only keep up but also stay ahead. Let’s push the boundaries of what’s possible with our data together!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data_science"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post shares key insights from Google's Community Circle.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Insights from Google’s Community Circle</title><link href="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/google_community_circle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insights from Google’s Community Circle"/><published>2024-04-28T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/google_community_circle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/google_community_circle/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/IMG_6343-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/IMG_6343-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/IMG_6343-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/IMG_6343.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Last Thursday (2024-04-25) marked a significant day as I joined fellow digital agencies at Google Amsterdam. We delved into the evolving landscape of digital marketing, focusing on the utilization of the Cloud, the burgeoning impact of AI, and the evolving role of agencies in this dynamic sector.</p> <h3 id="key-takeaways-from-the-event">Key Takeaways from the Event</h3> <p>The Power of a Robust Marketing Data Platform A robust marketing data platform (MDP) is no longer a luxury; it’s a necessity. It’s the cornerstone of digital transformation and a competitive edge in the fast-paced market. Google’s continued investment in Cloud services is a clear indicator of the direction in which the market is heading. This commitment underscores the importance of having a solid foundation upon which businesses can build and thrive.</p> <h3 id="generative-ai-a-tool-not-a-distraction">Generative AI: A Tool, Not a Distraction</h3> <p>Generative AI (GenAI) is making waves across industries, but it’s crucial not to get sidetracked. The priority should be to establish a solid MDP. This foundation is pivotal for mastering marketing mix modeling (MMM), attribution, and the exciting realm of predictive AI within marketing. It’s about laying the groundwork before embracing the advanced tools that AI offers.</p> <h3 id="the-roi-of-cloud-investments">The ROI of Cloud Investments</h3> <p>Investing in the Cloud is not just about staying current with technology; it’s about reaping tangible benefits. These investments translate into increased sales through enhanced customer understanding, establishing consistent and accurate data across organizations, and boosting the efficiency of marketing teams. In essence, the Cloud is a catalyst for not only understanding the present but also predicting and shaping the future.</p> <h3 id="creativity-in-a-technical-world">Creativity in a Technical World</h3> <p>As the market becomes increasingly technical, the value of creativity skyrockets. In a world where data and algorithms can suggest predictability, it’s the creative spark that differentiates and propels brands forward. Creativity is the human touch that complements the technical prowess of modern marketing tools.</p> <h3 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h3> <p>The session with other agencies was incredibly enriching. It provided a platform for sharing insights, challenging preconceptions, and collectively envisioning the future of our industry. As we navigate through the complexities of digital marketing, these gatherings are crucial for fostering collaboration and innovation.</p> <p>The journey ahead is exciting, and I am eager to explore the new frontiers of digital marketing with my peers.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Cloud"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog post shares key insights from Google's Community Circle.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Looking into the Future of Digital Marketing</title><link href="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/thinkmeasurement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Looking into the Future of Digital Marketing"/><published>2024-03-28T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-28T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/thinkmeasurement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/thinkmeasurement/"><![CDATA[<p>Navigating the precarious terrain of digital marketing in the AI-dominated landscape of 2024 presents a novel set of challenges and opportunities, devoid of the once-reliable guidance of cookies. Representing valantic NL, I recently attended Google’s #thinkmeasurement event in Dublin, an assembly dedicated to unraveling the complexities of this new era.</p> <p>The central theme of the event was adaptation. Engaging in dialogues with a spectrum of industry players—from agencies to advertisers—yielded profound insights into how we might navigate this uncharted territory. The past two years have seen many of us laying a robust foundation, cultivating a rich soil of data underpinned by a privacy-first philosophy. The task now is to leverage this data to its fullest potential.</p> <p>Artificial Intelligence stands as a beacon of immense potential, a tool that promises to redefine the boundaries of what’s possible in digital marketing. Yet, this technological narrative is only part of the story. The human element remains equally vital, heralding a significant transformation in how we approach our work processes, products, services, and organizational structures.</p> <p>As we stand on the cusp of 2024, the prospects are as exhilarating as they are daunting. The myriad interactions and presentations at the event have equipped me with a plethora of new ideas and refined concepts, ready to be tested in the real world. This moment in digital marketing is not just about confronting the challenges head-on; it’s about embracing the vast possibilities that lie ahead, guided by both innovative technology and the indispensable human touch.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Tracking_measurement"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a world where AI shapes the very fabric of digital marketing, professionals stand at the brink of a paradigm shift]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wrap up your Consent mode v2 implementation with this GTM-Template</title><link href="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/consentmodev2-extension.md/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wrap up your Consent mode v2 implementation with this GTM-Template"/><published>2024-02-29T12:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-29T12:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/consentmodev2-extension.md</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2024/consentmodev2-extension.md/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Per march 2024, Consent Mode v2 is mandatory</strong> It’s crucial to ensure that your implementation is up to date. If you’re already working on your Consent Mode V2 implementation, here’s a GTM template that can help you wrap it up effectively.</p> <p><strong>The Challenge with Ad-Specific Tags</strong> Imagine a scenario where a user clicks on your Google Shopping ad and lands on your website. The ‘view_item’ event is triggered, but hold on… the consent for ad-specific tags hasn’t been granted yet. The result? Your advertising tags, like Facebook’s ‘view_content’, are blocked.</p> <p><strong>The GTM Template Solution</strong> There’s a solution to this problem. By implementing a GTM-template, you can reactivate these events as soon as consent for advertising cookies is given. This ensures that you get a more complete picture of product and item list views in your advertising tools.</p> <p>How to Implement the GTM-template:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Download the Template:</strong> Grab the ‘template.tpl’ file from <a href="https://github.com/mohrstade/backTrack">the GitHub repository by mohrstade</a> and upload it to your GTM.</li> <li><strong>Modify the Script:</strong> We’ve made a slight modification: at the end of the script, we set ‘element.pushType’ back to null. This prevents your Google tags from being blocked later in the process.</li> <li><strong>Trigger the backTrack Tag:</strong> It should be triggered when consent was not yet known and as soon as it gets updated.</li> <li><strong>Block Google Tags:</strong> All Google tags that use Consent Mode should be blocked if pushType is equal to ‘artificial’.</li> <li><strong>Testing:</strong> Of course, test whether the script and all tags are working properly.</li> <li><strong>Configure Tags Early:</strong> Ensure that your configuration tags are triggered as early as possible; they can also be blocked due to lack of consent. Set them up so that they are also triggered on a consent update if it was not previously known.</li> </ol> <p><strong>The Impact of Small Tweaks</strong> Small tweaks can make a big difference in your data collection and interpretation. And isn’t that what Data &amp; Analytics is all about? Finding smart solutions that make our work more efficient and help us grow.</p> <p>I’m eager to hear about your experiences! Let’s make the world of e-commerce data a bit more comprehensible together.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Tracking_measurement"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The blog post provides a step-by-step guide for wrapping up your Consent Mode V2 implementation using a GTM template to ensure comprehensive tracking of ad-specific events]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflecting on a Year of Growth with the Data &amp;amp; Analytics Team</title><link href="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2023/reflection-2023/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflecting on a Year of Growth with the Data &amp;amp; Analytics Team"/><published>2023-12-27T00:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-27T00:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2023/reflection-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gitb33rman.github.io/blog/2023/reflection-2023/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>“Where do you want to be in a year?”</strong> That’s a question I was often asked when we started out.</p> <p>To be honest, I asked myself the same thing. Now, a year later, I look back with pride at the inception of our Data &amp; Analytics team.</p> <p>We’ve expanded from a duo to a tight-knit group of five.</p> <p>This year, we’ve completed over 70 projects for more than 40 clients.</p> <p>We’ve learned to work with tools like Google BigQuery, DBT, Terraform, PowerBI, Python, and SQL.</p> <p>It’s been a year of constant development, not just as a team but also as individuals.</p> <p>How did we manage this growth? Here are my key reflections:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Learning from others accelerates success</strong> - Sometimes it’s better not to reinvent the wheel but to learn from those who’ve already been there. A special thanks to the individuals who offered their invaluable help. With their support, we were able to accelerate our growth and learn important lessons.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Staying flexible in a changing world</strong> - The introduction of Google Analytics 4 brought many changes but also new opportunities. Suddenly, Google BigQuery became a crucial link for our analyses and reporting. The ability to adapt and innovate was key to our continued growth.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Collaboration creates strength</strong> - Without the collaboration with our clients and the synergy with our online marketing and platform teams, we could never have completed so many projects. Their contributions have helped us deliver better outcomes and create value with Data &amp; Analytics.</p> </li> </ol> <p>And if you ask me now where I want to be in a year? I’d say continuing on the same path: stable growth through collaboration, adaptability, and innovation.</p> <p>The introduction of generative AI and the challenges in marketing measurements are just two examples of the opportunities and challenges that 2024 has in store.</p> <p>I look forward to new opportunities, challenges, and especially to continue growing with my fantastic team. You were the heroes of this first chapter!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Strategic_leadership"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflecting on growth, collaboration, and the tools that propelled us forward]]></summary></entry></feed>